Guide to the Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection ARC.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Group 1: Teunis G. Bergen papers
  - Series 7: Surveying records, 1704-1877; 4.6 Linear Feet in 11 boxes.
    - Subseries 4: Maps and surveys, 1704-1879
      - New Lots, 1850-1866
        - Alexander, William, 1857 (Folder Flat File 22)
        - Belleplain, 1863 (Folder Flat File 21)
        - Miller, Horace A., 1854 (Folder Flat File 20)
        - Nichols, Walter, 1857 (Folder Flat File 19)
        - Pitkin, John R., 1857 (Box 35, Folder 1)
        - Plunders Neck, circa 1830-1881 (Folder Flat File 18)
        - Property Adjoining Cemetery of the Evergreens, 1859 (Box 30, Folder 1)
        - Sackman, Barbey and Delmonico, 1857 (Folder Flat File 17)
        - Sackmann, Jacob H., 1850-1851 (Box 35, Folder 2)
        - Sackmann, Jacob H. and Barbey, Andrew, 1853 (Box 35, Folder 3)
        - Suydam, Sarah A., 1860 (Folder Flat File 16)
        - Voorhees, John J., circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 11)
        - Warner, 1866 (Box 30, Folder 12)
        - Williams, Furman & Pellington, 1849 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - New Utrecht, 1857-1879
        - Langley, William, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 2)
        - Remsen, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 3)
        - Sedgwick, Theodore, 1857 (Box 30, Folder 4)
        - Seventh Avenue between 49th and 52nd Streets, circa 1856 (Box 30, Folder 5)
        - Stillwell, George, 1876 (Folder Flat File 15)
        - Stillwell, George, 1877 (Box 30, Folder 6)
        - Van Brunt, Rutgert, 1879 (Folder Flat File 14)
        - Voorhees, John J., circa 1830-1881 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Roads and Avenues, 1704-1875
        - Atlantic Avenue, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 7)
        - Cortelyou Lane, 1849 (Box 35, Folder 6)
        - Cowenhoven Property, 1841 (Folder Flat File 13)
        - De Russey Property, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 8)
        - Dyker Meadows, 1863 (Box OS-34)
        - First Avenue (at 67th St.), 1875 (Box 35, Folder 7)
        - Fort Hamilton, 1839 (Box 35, Folder 8)
        - Fort Hamilton, 1841 (Folder Flat File 12)
        - Fort Hamilton, 1846 (Folder Flat File 11)
        - Franklin Avenue, 1849-1850, 1860 (Box OS-34)
        - Gowanus to Flatbush, circa 1830-1881 (Box 35, Folder 9)
        - Gravesend, 1857 (Folder Flat File 10)
        - Gravesend to New Utrecht (copy), 1704 (Box 30, Folder 9)
        - Johnson's Lane (near George Suydam's Property), circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 10)
        - Lefferts Farm, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 11)
        - New Utrecht to 38th St., 1851 (Box 35, Folder 10)
        - New Utrecht to Brooklyn, 1856 (Folder Flat File 9)
        - New Utrecht to Bay Ridge, 1855 (Folder Flat File 8)
        - Nostrand Avenue - grades, circa 1830-1881 (Folder Flat File 7)
        - Nostrand Ave, Rogers Ave., Crown St., Carrol St. - Topographical surveys, circa 1830-1881 (Folder Flat File 6)
        - School House (New Utrecht), 1854 (Box 30, Folder 12)
        - Sewer to Fresh Creek, circa 1830-1881 (Folder Flat File 5)
          Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
          This map is folded once due to it's size. The map should be laid out on a large table free from obstructions.
        - Stewart Avenue, 1844 (Folder Flat File 4)
        - Third Avenue, 1837 (Folder Flat File 3)
        - Third Avenue, 1839 (Box 35, Folder 11)
        - York Street, 1862 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      - South Hampton, circa 1830-1881
        - Shinecock Hills, South Hampton, Long Island - water survey, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      - Yellow Hook, 1852
        - Richards, Daniel, 1852 (Folder Flat File 2)
      - Index to Maps and Surveys (Bound Volume) (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Subseries 5: Map tracings and land descriptions, 1833-1877
      - Bay Ridge Avenue, circa 1830-1881 (Folder Flat File 1)
      - Bay Street, 1857 (Box 30, Folder 16)
      - Bergen Cemetery Plots, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 17)
      - Bergen, Hans Hansen, circa 1830-1881 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      - Bergen, Teunis G. (New Utrecht), 1833-1834 (Box 30, Folder 19)
      - Coney Island, circa 1830-1881 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      - Delaplaine, John, circa 1850 (Box 30, Folder 20)
      - Denyse & Martins, circa 1830-1881 (Box 35, Folder 13)
      - Eighth Ward, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Ekhart, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Emmans Property, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Fifth Avenue, 1855 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Flatland Neck, 1877 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Flatlands, 1876 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - Fort Hamilton, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - Gravesend, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - Hackley's Lots, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - Hayman & Voorhees Property, 1865 (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - Hunts Dock, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - Kent, H.A., circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - King, William, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 13)
      - Ludlam, Silas, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 14)
      - New Utrecht, 1874 (Box 31, Folder 15)
      - New York Harbor, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 16)
      - Ninth Street, 1850 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - Schenck Property, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 18)
      - Suydam Woodland, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 19)
      - Terhune Property, 1852 (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Subseries 6: Specifications of houses, 1734-1855
      - Bennet, Cornelius, 1855 (Box 31, Folder 21)
      - Bergen, Garret, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 22)
      - Bergen, Lefferts, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 23)
      - Bergen, Michael, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 24)
      - Bergen, P.G., circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 25)
      - Bergen, Teunis G., 1841, 1844 (Box 31, Folder 26)
      - Bergen, Teunis G. - Enlargement of home, circa 1841-1881 (Box 35, Folder 14)
      - Berry, John, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 27)
      - Board of Sewer Commissioners - Contract (Blank), 1864 (Box 31, Folder 28)
      - Brower, Abraham & Van Vechte, Nicholas, 1734 (Box 31, Folder 29)
      - Church plans, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 30)
      - Elrath, Thomas, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 31)
      - Johnson St. & Stanton St., circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 32)
      - Kouwenhoven, George, circa 1830-1881 (Box 31, Folder 33)
      - Lott, James C., circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Lunatic Asylum - Carpenter's Specifications, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - Murphy, Henry C. & Wiley, John S., 1849 (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - Rule for Length of Rafters/Draft of Steps for a House, nd (Box 32, Folder 4)
      - School House, New Utrecht, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 5)
      - South Brooklyn Building Association, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 6)
      - South Reformed Dutch Church, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 7)
      - Tin Roofs, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 8)
      - Unidentified Homes, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Subseries 7: Title searches, 1851-1865
      - Bennet, John, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 10)
      - Bennet, Winant, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 11)
      - Bergen, Tunis, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 12)
      - Carson, Deborah, 1854 (Box 32, Folder 13)
      - Church, James C., circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 14)
      - Cropsey, Garret, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 15)
      - Denyse, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 16)
      - Denyse & Barkeloo Families, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 17)
      - Emmans, George V., circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 18)
      - Flatbush Avenue (For Grading Assessment), circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 19)
      - Flatbush Avenue (For Maps), circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 20)
      - Gelston, George S., 1853 (Box 32, Folder 21)
      - Hoerschgen, Arnold, 1870 (Box 32, Folder 22)
      - Kibbee, George, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 23)
      - Lake, Derrick, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 24)
      - Lefferts Farm, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 25)
      - New Utrecht, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 26)
      - Smith, Jane, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 27)
      - Turnbull Farm, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 28)
      - Van Nuys, Annatie, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 29)
      - Van Pelt, Tunis, 1851 (Box 32, Folder 30)
      - Voorhees, John, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 31)
      - Wisner, William, 1865 (Box 32, Folder 32)
      - Wyckoff, John, circa 1830-1881 (Box 32, Folder 33)
- Group 2: Bergen family and Bergen extended family papers
  - Series 1: Bergen family papers, 1696-1893; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 box.
    Bergen family papers comprises various papers of Teunis Bergen's family members. Of particular interest is a folder of Bergen family land records dated 1696-1700, including maps of Hans Hansen Bergen's land. Also included are papers pertaining to Teunis G. Bergen's father, Garret Bergen; his first cousin once removed, Cornelius Bergen; his wife, Jane Bergen; his younger cousin, John C. Bergen; his brother, Peter G. Bergen; and his son, Garret T. Bergen. The types of records include school papers, certificates of appointment to civil and military appointments, land deeds, mortgages, as well as a bill of sale for a slave once owned by Cornelius Bergen.
    - Bergen family correspondence (miscellaneous), 1841, 1864-1881 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Bergen Land Records, 1696-1700 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Bergen, Cornelius - Appointment to Captain of the King's County Militia, April 14, 1797 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Bergen, Cornelius - Commission as Wreckmaster, 1835, ca. 1865 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Bergen, Cornelius - Slave bill of sale, 1800-1801 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Bergen, Garret - Deeds, 1828, 1839 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Bergen, Garret - Estate papers, 1843-1846 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Bergen, Garret T. - Commissions to the New York State Militia, 1851, 1859 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Bergen, Jane - Estate papers, 1865-1872 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Bergen, John C. - Mortgage, 1865 (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Bergen, John C. - School Papers, 1842 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Bergen, Peter G. - Resolution of the Brooklyn Board of Education on the occcasion of his death, 1865 (Box 33, Folder 12)
    - Bergen, Van Brunt - Correspondence (incoming), circa 1881-1888 (Box 33, Folder 13)
    - Bergen, Van Brunt - Surveys and notes on Bay Ridge, 1890-1893 (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - Maps and drawings, 1814-1880 (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence and receipts, 1871-1882 (Box 33, Folder 16)
    - Photostats of three letters written from Holland to the Voorhees family in America, 1600-1699 (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - Tintypes (Box Tintypes 1)
  - Series 2: Bergen extended family papers, 0.1 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
    Bergen extended family papers is organized into three subseries and primarily concerns family genealogies and family members' estates. Conover/Cowenhoven family papers comprises legal documents and correspondence between Bergen and various members of the Conover and Cowenhoven families. Included are the estate papers of Johanna Conover (Bergen's first cousin), as well as Elizabeth and Phebe Cowenhoven. The documents reveal that Bergen was named executor of all three of these estates. Also included are letters from Conover family members, including George S. Conover, President of the town of Seneca, New York (1873-1875). Cortelyou family papers consists of correspondence between Teunis G. Bergen and various members of the Cortelyou family, primarily concerning Cortelyou genealogy. Included are letters from his son-in-law, Peter L. Cortelyou, the last wills and testaments of Mary and Maria Cortelyou, and deeds and abstracts of Cortelyou family land holdings. Wyckoff family papers consists primarily of correspondence between Teunis G. Bergen and members of his wife's family, the Wyckoffs. It also includes documents pertaining to the estate and last will and testament of Peter Wyckoff.
    - Subseries 1: Conover/Cowenhoven family papers, 1820-1881
      - Conover, Catharine - Correspondence, 1814, 1821 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Conover Family - Correspondence, 1820-1878 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Conover, Johanna - Estate papers, 1864-1866 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Conover, Johanna - Last will and testament, 1861, 1866 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      - Cortelyou, Peter L. - Correspondence, 1878-1880 (Box 34, Folder 5)
      - Cowenhoven, A. - Last will and testament, circa 19th century (Box 34, Folder 6)
      - Cowenhoven, Elizabeth - Estate papers, 1870-1877 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      - Cowenhoven, Elizabeth - Last will and testament, 1857-1876 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - Cowenhoven, Elizabeth - Legal papers, 1870 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      - Cowenhoven Family - Correspondence, 1833-1881 (Box 34, Folder 10)
      - Cowenhoven, Phebe - Correspondence, 1854-1867 (Box 34, Folder 11)
      - Cowenhoven, Phebe - Estate papers, 1852-1876 (Box 34, Folder 12)
      - Dutch Letter, circa 19th century (Box 34, Folder 13)
      - Suydam and Conover - Account Records, 1858-1864 (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Subseries 2: Cortelyou family papers
      - Cortelyou Family - Miscellaneous correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1846-1880 (Box 34, Folder 15)
      - Cortelyou, Ida - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1854-1862 (Box 34, Folder 16)
      - Cortelyou, Mary - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1851-1878 (Box 34, Folder 17)
      - Cortelyou, Mary and Maria - Last wills and testaments, circa 1855, 1865 (Box 34, Folder 18)
      - Cortelyou, Peter - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1859-1860 (Box 34, Folder 19)
      - Cortelyou, Peter - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1858-1870 (Box 34, Folder 20)
      - Cortelyou, Peter - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1859 (Box 34, Folder 21)
      - Cortelyou, Peter - Correspondence to his father, 1873-1881 (Box 34, Folder 22)
      - Cortelyou, Peter - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1857-1875 (Box 34, Folder 23)
      - Cortelyou, Peter - Map of farm in New Jersey, circa 19th century (Box 34, Folder 24)
    - Subseries 3: Wyckoff family papers, 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 box.
      - Wyckoff, Isaac - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1863-1872 (Box 34, Folder 25)
      - Wyckoff, John - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1858-1873 (Box 34, Folder 26)
      - Wyckoff, Nicholas - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1844-1867 (Box 34, Folder 27)
      - Wyckoff, Peter - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1848-1865 (Box 34, Folder 28)
      - Wyckoff, Peter - Estate settlement, 1835-1847 (Box 34, Folder 29)
      - Wyckoff, Peter - Estate Settlement, account book, 1825-1847 (Box 34, Folder 30)
      - Wyckoff, Peter - Last will and testament, February 8, 1819 (Box 34, Folder 31)
      - Wyckoff, Richard - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1853-1872 (Box 34, Folder 32)
      - Wyckoff, Van Brunt - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1853-1872 (Box 34, Folder 33)
      - Wyckoff, William F. - Correspondence to Teunis G. Bergen, 1865-1881 (Box 34, Folder 34)
      - Wyckoff Family - Miscellaneous items and correspondence, 1877 (Box 34, Folder 35)